[Music]
okay so in this video we're going to be
talking about change blindness and
change blindness ISM it comes up a lot
in cognitive psychology especially when
people are trying to test memory so when
we talk about memory we mostly focus on
the short term and long term forms of
memory but that's not the whole story
we also have sensory memory and you can
kind of think of this as a short
short-term memory so to illustrate the
sensory store let's do a quick task here
are the instructions you are going to
see two images and they are identical
almost they are different in one
significant way try to find the change
get ready
three two one
all right did you spot the change if you
didn't don't worry most people find this
actually really difficult
the one-second visual mask that you saw
that interferes with everything in your
visual sensory store that's also called
your iconic memory let's try this one
more time but this time let's use a 100
millisecond visual mask alright get
ready here we go
okay so did you notice the shadow the
shadow of the tree is what changed that
time that should have been much easier
than the first time we tried this that
1/10 of a second delay is short enough
so that you've retained nearly
everything in your visual sensory store
so that whenever you look at those two
images it's really easy to compare to
find the difference between those two
images what you've just done is called a
flicker task it's used a lot in
cognitive psychology when people fail to
see the change between those pictures
that's called change blindness now let's
look at a couple more examples this time
we're going to manipulate the mass
between the images because this shorter
that visual mask is the less change
blindness you should see so let's start
out with a 100 millisecond mask
so have you noticed the change yet if
you haven't don't really strain your
eyes just kind of look at the full
picture and it may pop out at you do you
notice the colors on the girl's shirt
okay so that was that should've been a
much easier example than the first one
that we tried because we were using a
very short mask that was only 100
milliseconds or a tenth of a second now
let's try one more this time without any
masks okay so this one should be the
easiest of them all in case you don't
see it just check the top of the
astronauts head now why does this so
much easier than the first view that we
tried because this time we don't have a
visual mask
in other words won't have anything to
disrupt our sensory memory so we're
directly able to compare the memory for
one picture for the next picture in the
difference between those two pictures
pops out right at us so if we have less
change blindness the shorter that visual
mask goes only opposite should be true
right if we increase the visual mask
then we should experience more change
blindness to put another way it should
be harder to detect the change so let's
do that let's pull up one more example
this time we'll use a mask of one whole
second that's twice what we've been
doing so far so to get ready here it
comes
all right so this should be considerably
harder than all of the other ones you've
done so far now the weird thing about
this is that I actually expanded the
total playtime so for example the other
ones that you looked at you only got to
see the pictures for about a second and
a half this time you get to see this
picture two and a half seconds at a time
and yet that mask which is a whole
second long makes this really really
difficult so what I want to do now I'm
going to move that mask down to 100
milliseconds against we're gonna move it
back down to a tenth of a second and
then we'll see how well you do so
remember don't necessarily scan across
the picture just let your eyes wander
just gaze upon the picture and with the
short mask time it may pop out at you if
it hasn't yet that's okay this is a
little bit of a tricky one so what I'm
gonna do now is I'm just going to get
rid of the mask completely and that
should eliminate any kind of effects of
change blindness that we see because
we'll be able to directly compare one
visual image with the other visual image
that's held in our sensory memory yeah
and now it pops out at you right so now
we don't have any change blindness any
longer because we're able to directly
compare those two images held in our
sensory memory so why does this actually
happen it's because iconic memory allows
us to perceive the world as a fluid
experience is not fragmented so in that
way this is a good thing these very
small changes in our environment like
what you saw in these pictures are
rarely that important and so we have a
habit of missing them so let me give you
two more examples and both of these are
only video clips just watch them and see
if you can spot any kind of change just
like you did in the flicker task that we
just did all right here we go
with your house yeah
messy right now I just got off work it's
nice you got air conditioning
I saw hey I kept a scrapbook of your
clippings and everything there you are
I got to running I ran a long way it's a
long time listen Forrest I don't know
how to say this
I just I want to apologize for anything
that I ever did to you cuz I was messed
up for a long time and this is my friend
from Alabama how did you okay so did you
see the change if you didn't that's okay
it was kind of an innocuous change it
wasn't really important had nothing to
do with the plot it was just something
it was going on in the background when
we first enter Jenny's apartment you see
that this iron is up right now after
they've been talking now we see it a few
seconds later on its side face down now
we didn't see any character touch this
and it's very unlikely that there's a
poltergeist or anything like that that's
affecting this it's just a continuity
error we experienced change blindness
all the time movies because these
changes rarely matter they're not that
important let's look at one more example
[Music]
been away now I'm back
believe me mr. Torrence it's good to see
you
it's good to be back Lloyd what Laspisa
hair the dog that bit me bourbon on the
rocks I don't do it
no choice do mr. Torrence no charge
your money's no good here
orders from the house
drink up mr. Thomas
I'm the kind of man likes to know who's
buying their drinks Lloyd
it's not a matter that concerns you mr.
Taurus at least not at this point
anything you say Loyd anything you say
okay did you spot the change if you
didn't then hey that's another example
of change blindness but just in case you
didn't let's walk back through the scene
one more time we're at the bartender you
can see he's pouring this glass for Jack
you noticed one big ice cube in this
glass we cut back to the bartender back
to Jack and now the ice cube has
apparently melted in the span of ten
seconds back to the bartender and then
back to Jack and now the ice cube has
reappeared in his glass back to the
bartender one final time and then over
to Jack with his final shot and you see
that what do you know the ice is gone
once more so most people don't notice
this because they're too busy focusing
on the dialogue between Jack and the
bartender because that's what's most
important in the scene so we experience
change blindness everywhere all the time
it's not just in movies it's not just in
television and usually this is not a bad
thing imagine if you notice every single
change in your daily life you'd
constantly be distracted by all these
changes happening that's all that I have
for this video thanks for tuning in bye
[Music]
you